<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
	<title>Type options</title>

	Commands that deal with values such as <quote>read</quote>,
	<quote>write</quote>, <quote>search</quote> and <quote>measure</quote>
	take a common set of options that are called the type options.
	These options are used to describe the value.

	The <quote>--type</quote> option specifies the type of the value.
	The following types are available:

	<list>
		<item>byte</item>
		<item>integer</item>
		<item>ieee754</item>
		<item>text</item>
		<item>address</item>
		<item>instruction</item>
	</list>

	The following sections will describe each one and their specific
	options.

	<section>
		<title>Byte</title>

		This is the most basic type of them all. It represents a unit
		of memory. Its size is always 1. When printed, the sequence of
		bits that form it are represented as an unsigned integer in
		hexadecimal notation.

		This type does not have specific options.
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Integer</title>

		An integer number can be represented in various ways. Proctal
		supports 8, 16, 32 and 64 bit wide integers, either unsigned or
		using the two's complement representation for negative numbers
		and either in little or big endian. It's printed with decimal
		numbers.

		The <quote>--integer-endianness</quote> option can be used
		to set the endianness. You can choose between
		<quote>big</quote> and <quote>little</quote>.

		The <quote>--integer-bits</quote> option can be used to set
		the number of bits. Only <quote>8</quote>, <quote>16</quote>,
		<quote>32</quote> and <quote>64</quote> are supported at the
		moment.

		The <quote>--integer-sign</quote> option can be used to set
		the sign representation. <quote>twos-complement</quote> uses
		two's complement. <quote>unsigned</quote> disregards signing
		altogether.

		By default an integer is 8-bit, signed using two's complement
		and using the same endianness that the system uses.
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>IEEE754</title>

		These numbers are represented as defined by the IEEE 754-1985
		standard. It's printed with decimal numbers.

		The <quote>--ieee754-precision</quote> option allows you to
		pick the precision. You may use <quote>single</quote>,
		<quote>double</quote> or <quote>extended</quote>.

		By the default a floating point number uses single precision.
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Text</title>

		Text is a single character from a character set. It's printed
		in UTF-8.

		The <quote>--text-encoding</quote> option defines the
		charater set to use. At the moment the only value that is
		supported is <quote>ascii</quote>.

		By default text uses the ASCII encoding.
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Address</title>

		This represents a memory address in the computer. It's printed
		in hexadecimal notation.

		This type does not have type specific options.
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Instruction</title>

		This represents a CPU instruction. It's printed in assembly.

		The <quote>--instruction-arch</quote> option defines the
		architecture of the instruction. You may use
		<quote>x86</quote>, <quote>x86-64</quote>, <quote>arm</quote>
		and <quote>aarch64</quote>.

		By default the architecture is the same as the tool was
		compiled in.

		The <quote>--instruction-syntax</quote> option defines the
		syntax for assembly. You may use either <quote>att</quote> or
		<quote>intel</quote>.

		By default <quote>intel</quote> is used.
	</section>
</document>
